I was wondering if we could speak about
lying
the phenomenon fly the choice to lie so
a simple question isn't wrong to lie
where can we go with it
sure it is so now you can ask why is it
wrong to lie and don't just take it as
an as an authority was it to declared
the lying is wrong and now you must obey
by it
yeah lying is wrong but you won't
investigate why it is wrong so what's
the first most obvious thing that shows
itself if you start to investigate why
lying would be wrong
what is lying dishonesty but okay so
what it like dishonesty lying concealing
what all those things have in common you
not wanting something exactly which
means something is but you want to be
different so in its nature it's a it's a
it's a it's a discrepancy it's a fun of
it's a contradiction two opposing things
one is the truth the other one is what
you would prefer to be but the problem
with lying is phenol logically speaking
from a point from a point of view of a
person who who practices mindfulness
tries their wisdom the problem lying is
that you can't you cannot deny the truth
without implying that without giving
importance to a point of view or the
truth so that's what lying is
practically wrong lying is practically
an obstacle for developing wisdom if you
could say theoretically lie without
diverting that existential order of
truth in my point of view then lying
would not be unwholesome but it is
impossible to engage in an act of la
lying without implicitly immediately
fueling the wrong order whereby it's my
point of view my preference that comes
first truth is second and when I say truth
truth is second and when I say truth
I mean factual presence of a cellphone
isn't phenomena and that's the key here
it's not like the truth there is a line
and there is a truth no you denying well
you denied that whatever the truth is at
the time by serving a lie means you
implicitly also overriding the the most
self-evident basic nature of there is an
experience that it comes first
structurally first your point of view is
structurally second so by engaging in in
a lie you're engaging in perversion of
that order that's when a little lie is
as bad as a as a bad lie as a big lie
from the point of view of the mind that
wants to practice because practice means
undoing any perversion to the essential
order of the five aggregates in the same
sense like you cannot engage in a
sensual act without central perceptions
being implied and central perceptions
are central distortions so in other
words you can't engage in sensuality
without having without being distorted
by sensuality at the same time without
fueling already persisting distortion of
central perception so you can't engage
in a lie without fueling the existential
Distortion basically of there is an
phenomenon the truth the self-evident
arising of of whatever is present izing
the there are reason experience is there
on its own means my attitude my actions
upon it are only because this thing
allows it allows my actions to be a
possibility in other words if there is
no sape unpleasant feeling manifested
would you be even able to conceive
acting out of an unpleasant feeling to
try to get rid of it you wouldn't
hold on a less fundamental level if
there's there's something like I don't
know take some experience you you have to go
take some experience you you have to go
to work that's your a reason situation
they possess there that has its
significance like things you have to do
reasons why you have to do it because
you need to earn money you need to do
this you need to provide
so that's your factual situation on
account of it you'll be acting left and
right and so on and deciding but when
you start engaging in a act of lying
you're overriding that very order
doesn't mean you can change the order
like there's still things a reason on
their own but you are fully gratuitously
giving priority to your point of view
that in itself at that time is is based
on that simply on ignoring what the real
order is so in other words you start
lying about having to go to work lying
to yourself not even lying to others you
sir saying no you don't need to go to
work because really you don't want to go
to work so you start lying because the
reason thing is unbearable or not
necessarily unbearable but it's
unpleasant and you don't want to have to
deal with it so that's why another
another aspect of an act of lying is
it's always rooted in in avoiding
displeasure why else would you be lying
unless you yourself perceived that if
you don't admit the truth you will avoid
that displeasure the pain of that truth
but can you really avoid the pain
through sort of looking elsewhere you
can't you're only acting out of it exactly exactly
exactly exactly
but see the fact that you engaged in an
act of lie means you do have you have
well you had it before and now you're
maintaining the belief that you can
avoid the reason pressure of the truth
the displeasure of the truth simply by lying
displeasure of the truth simply by lying
which then means implies that you can
avoid existentially a reason phenomena
simply by providing another phenomenon
so it's fundamentally rooted actor lying
is firmly rooted in a wrong view that's
why it's fundamentally unwholesome and
and it's the same with any of the
presets that the Buddha laid out none of
them are like universally given
Commandments all of them are rooted in
the in the principle of greed aversion
delusion which separately individually
are all also principles of some form of
contradicting there is a nature of
experience which is why it's unwholesome
they're not unwholesome because it's a
it's a universal morality applied to
their unwholesome because they go
against how things have arisen and
that's how you can know for yourself
that they are and also once you
understand the nature of things how they
have arisen so then you have a criteria
for what what skillful what's an
skillful what wholesome words and
wholesome so that's what line is always
wrong because it always goes against the
because it always goes against the
principle against the nature of a no
reason thing whatever that thing is so
the example we gave you don't want to go
and do this particular work now you can
admit that you can you don't have to lie
to yourself but that means now you have
to take responsibility for the
displeasure you are feeling oh the work
needs to be done but I choose not to
which means all the reasons they were
making me do this work supporting my
family learning whatever else necessary
whatever else was the motivation for
working I'm now responsible for not
meeting any of those requirements so
when when when when down the line
circumstances remind me of that my
family starts asking for money or I get
sick and I can't pay for my treatment
and so on it's because I chose to not do
this particular work so I'm responsible
for that so now this future misfortune
that came as a result of not being able
to look after yourself is because you
chose not to look
after yourself it's nothing wrong with
that that's the thing you have every
right to choose to know but that means
you must take responsibility for what
comes out of it but now that means oh by
trying to avoid the responsibility of
doing my duty
for example now actually paying the
price which is not even worse now I
can't provide for the family I don't
have enough money for this I don't have
enough money for that I don't have
enough money for food and that's on you
the result of your choice to avoid work
and that's very implicit you have to
admit that it's on you so now all this
and it can endure for weeks a month for
what for as long as you don't get out of
that situation but it's still a
responsible thing to do admit the weight
of your choices but it's way too easy to
not admit it only if only you find
another reason for you not doing the
work apart from you not wanting to do
the work and that's the nature of bad
faith and is essentially philosophy
which is like it's it's like lying but
not quite lying because you you're not
necessarily fully self aware of the
truth because it's the very truth you're
trying to cover up for yourself so now
if I say well I couldn't work because of
such-and-such whatever things came like
I couldn't work because he was raining
it's not like oh I couldn't work because
I chose rain to be the reason for my not
working but if you say no it was raining
so I couldn't work which means now when
I don't have enough money it's because
it's the way this fault
so you bypass responsibility for not
working at the time and then
consequently for all the future issues
that came out that there were results of
not working are also bypassed could see
it's not on me that's why people always
inherently is the easiest thing to blame
another or to blame circumstances
and that's that unauthenticated should
we speak about often in in our videos
because unless you take responsibility
on that fundamental level you'll never
have a basis for Dhamma to apply and
fundamental responsibility is suffering
again like you don't want to work
because it's unpleasant you want to
accept future responsibility for the
consequences of your not working because
it's unpleasant so fundamentally you
don't want to suffer and you keep
avoiding this pleasure is the only mean
of dealing with suffering that you know
but it doesn't deal with it
evading suffering can only be done
because suffering has a reason that's
the truth this pleasure is manifested
and you're liable to future
manifestation of this pleasure that's
the truth that you will never understand
because all your actions revolver walk
are around avoiding that very truth and
then lying to other people is just
extension of this very principle so you
can't undo that principle as in lying to
yourself unless you stop habitually
lying to other people but stopping to
stopping ceasing to lie to other people
doesn't necessarily mean you will
automatically undo lying to yourself
that takes a further effort but that
further effort is only possible on the
basis of the first effort of stop lying
to others stop proliferate stop
maintaining basically the proliferating
that wrong order of things through your
acts of lying to others so you reduce it
a bit and then you will be able to stop
lying to yourself as well and that's how
you can accept responsibility and
suffering as I said is the fundamental
responsibility see you can say oh I
suffer because he said this or I suffer
because I didn't get enough or I suffer
because you know I lost my family or
something like that and if those things
were truly rooted in sorry if suffering
was truly rooted in those things yeah
you wouldn't be able to be free from it
but as the Buddha himself understood and
then thought what is it
fortunately it isn't rooted in those
things it's rooted in your resistance of
the disagreeable things that come your
way but those are two different things
but for as long as your actions maintain
the view that it's in the things in what
he said or she said what I had what I
lost you will never take responsibility
for suffering as and you will never take
responsibility for your resistance to
the disagreeable experience and because
of that you will always remain affected
by the disagreeable experience so the
only way to stop resisting disagreeable
experience is to take responsibility for
the disagreeable experience
noelite yourself consequently you won't
be lying to others that's where our hand
cannot lie he became incapable of lying
to himself where the problem is because
he solved the problem yes the key don't
lie to yourself yeah but in order to not
lie to yourself you have to stop a bit
realign to others yeah again so it's not
as bad but if you if you have to be
strict and you to see does it per take
in the principle of lying principle
you're trying to undo principle of of
perverting the order of existence
putting the blame where the blame isn't
and if you look at the whitelighter
stuff yet it's still pivoting why would
you wide line because you don't want
discomfort why you don't want discomfort
because you're blaming discomfort for
pain which means by not wanting
discomfort you are avoiding
responsibility for resisting the
discomfort and blaming the discomfort
for your suffering
so I'll just wide lie quickly so I don't
get discomfort with I won't suffer no
you don't suffer when you don't resist
it's not that you don't suffer when
there is no discomfort aaron has
discomfort he is no suffering
so that's why white lies are bad after
any few if you could save somebody from
suffering future by lying away ways this
person hiding you know these people are
looking for this right well
fundamentally you're rubies are the most
fundamental level the reasons for
erection are always selfish it cannot be
otherwise like you choose to help others
because that's what's gonna make you
happy well you choose to help others
because that's how you you gonna avoid
personal discomfort so others are always
secondary so it's not going the only way
to go about this is to accept it
and then stop perverting the order as we
as we just spoke about so stop blaming
the circumstances for your suffering but
recognize that it's in you resisting the
circumstances that's what suffering is
rooted so when like you're hiding a
fugitive or something and then you lie
to others like no I don't know where
that person is yeah you saving their
life maybe if that's at stake I don't
know but what you're really acting out
of is you being responsible for choosing
to to to sort of have them in the first
place and then secondly for not wanting
to experience discomfort of
responsibility because if you say the
truth they'll find that person and then
things might have the person and you
will be unable to not blame yourself and
blaming yourself it's unpleasant so
really you just want to prevent
circumstances to allow you to engage in
self blaming that's it so you're doing
it for yourself but that's what it would
have said in the suit does it often
mention like if some if a person who is
truthful to himself truthful to others
if he
question by kings of authorities have
you seen this you will say yes I've seen
it if he hasn't seen it he'll say no I
haven't seen it he won't say one or the
other for no-one's sake he'll say the
truth why because you say the truth and
if these people that are chasing a
fugitive choose to do certain things
with a fugitive that's not only you even
if you say yes he went into that house
that's not on you what they choose to do
with him or why or to what extent that's
not on you on you is to not pervert the
extension order from your point of view
because by doing so you're giving
priority to your point of view which
means it's a slippery slope you act out
of avoiding discomfort means you're
going to be acting out of prolonging
pleasure which means you're going to be
acting out of conceit out of delusion
out of and that those are the reasons
for your own suffering not the
circumstances you'll be subjected to so
basically practically through trying to
avoid suffering you end up making
yourself more and more liable to
suffering on that existential level and
it's no lying or stealing or cheating no
killing not negotiable because without
that basis you cannot overcome the
attitude of avoiding responsibility for
their own existence and further on
suffering you just can't even if you
want to there's a major offense for monk
if you lies about you know having
attained a superior state you know well
cuz the consequences on it like the
results of your action that's why people
take what you say is truth well exactly
yeah and you can spread for generations
and people will then be acting out of
that as the truth while in reality it
isn't the truth in other words as the
Buddha described in in some other
suitors you know like giving to an
enlightened being making offering to to
an like somebody who's factory
awakening free from suffering he's the
greatest merit so if somebody's
factually or there is a word that
such-and-such is factually free from
suffering he's a nutter hunt
oh I quickly gonna make some merry
because giving to that verse is gonna
have much more merit then given to just
any anybody else who isn't enlightened
if that's the truth you will actually
get all those results that great merit
because the person is factual in our end
let's say somebody spreads a lie that is
in our hand and nobody knows it's a lie
and if people go out of their way and
they don't give to others because they
want to give to dissident
and in reality he isn't in around so the
whole mess created was because somebody
lied that that person is not hunt says
the direct result of that lie millions
have been misguided Oh many people have
been misguided and they've been acting
as if the persons in our hunt being sure
they're gonna get all this merit
dedicating all the offerings to their
one person because he's not an intern
that he isn't so they've been deceived
directly as a result of that lie which
means the person who lied is going to be
responsible for that mass deception
cause which kid is a as I said can last
for generations so that's why it's bad
you say that the monk could be deceiving
himself which then deceives others yeah
but that's different that's why like
that's why it's not an offense if among
does that are out of over estimation
that that's my men when I said like
lying to others it's not quite on the
same level as lying to yourself because
lying to yourself means obscuring the
truth so simply through obscuring the
truth you're lying to yourself but when
you come to lie to others means you're
fully aware of what truth is being
obscured and then you act completely the
opposite way so it's an extra layer so
that's what the attitude of bad faith
avoiding responsibility it's not like
fully-fledged as lying to another person because in
as lying to another person because in
order to
I you need to know what the truth is you
can't lie if you think what you're
saying is the truth
yeah but when it comes to yourself it's
not that clear-cut because you're
already refusing to admit what the truth
is so you're refusing to be fully aware
of what the truth is
which means you can't like fully lie to
yourself because in order to fully lie
to yourself you need to fully admit the
truth to yourself but lying to yourself
it's not on the level of actually lying
to yourself but it's on a level of
repressing or pressing like turning away
ignoring the truth that were VJs
ignorance it's autumn like a
metaphysical lack of information of what
the universe is it's ignoring what's
right in front of you and lying to
others comes on the basis of that
principle it's just further proliferated
and it's the sustaining of the thing oh
yeah yeah lying is the lifeblood of
addiction sure sure but you could say
that the lifeblood of lying is avoiding
self itself it's avoiding responsibility
for your own experience so basically the
basis for lying is is attitude of bad
faith to yourself as in having faith in
ignoring not in what you're actually
ignoring that'll mean you prefer the
order the only way you can ignore
something is because it's there but you
focus on prioritizing the act of
ignoring not the act of what's already
there and that's the most fundamental
attitude towards the experience the
arisia turning a blind eye in only way you can
turning a blind eye in only way you can
turn a blind eye to something is if that
thing is already there so the most
fundamental attitudes of turning a blind
eye is that fundamental wrong view in
regard to the nature of existence being
I have not my own as in I'm not in
control of this of this body upon which
my whole life depends I'm subject to
aging I'm subject to death suffering all
these things are obvious but the only
reason people do not resolve them is
because they give priority to ignoring
them and that's what I mean you give
rusty to your point of view on account
of what's there in regard to which you
exercise your point of here and that's
why ignoring their ignorance it's like a
vicious circle a VJ leads to more
eligium ignoring leads to maintenance of
the attitude of ignoring so what do I
need to stop ignoring then to undo the
entire video of the whole samsara stop
ignoring theories and feelings stop
ignoring there isn't intentions
and that's why person who has made that
effort and stop denoting these things
will become incapable of engaging in
your will anger lying cheating even
sensuality because sensuality in itself
it's already that perversion on a
fundamental level finding pleasurable in
that which is truly ugly so you ignore
that it's ugly
ignorance of the ugly is the basis for
attraction ignoring the ugly yeah
ignoring the unattractiveness the
fundamental on attractiveness the
fundamental kind of dispassion or
absence of passion in it ignoring that
is how you have maintained passion in it
what's the nature of consumer well in
this in the suitors and often you know
in many of them in the buddhist fridays
you often hear about delusion greed
aversion delusion no but they'll say no
ha so you know people can get their
Heather on greed to get their head
around aversion
but often delusion is kind of regarded
as is something that's not directly my
responsibility in as much as greedy's or
aversion yeah so it's kind of steets
regarded in a sort of a semi
metaphysical sense as in it's there but
it's it's not really something i can
directly experience but actually it is
delusion is an attitude of your mind in
as much greed or lust and aversion are
otherwise you wouldn't have been
mentioned always like that
so from that point of view delusion it's
more of like an attitude of indolence
laziness choice to keep things cloudy
exactly keeping it opaque intentionally not
keeping it opaque intentionally not
looking turning a blind eye distracting
yourself intentionally with things
they're gonna take your mind away from
yourself so you realize delusion is a
very active thing and as the Bell said
that's why it's the most blame word
actually because it's the hardest to
undo as well but the fact that you can
undo it means it's not this metaphysical
lack of knowledge it's your very
attitude that it's even more fundamental
than the attitude of last and I'm a
digital version they're kind of
secondary to it lust requires a basis of
delusion a version requires the basis of
delusion delusion requires basis of
delusion so if you're deluded through
and through not because you don't know
certain things but because you
perpetually act out of ignorance
they then maintains yourself in the
situation of ignorance and situation of
ignorance again it's not ignorance
ignorance as in you don't know something
it's you actively ignoring and giving
priority to the ignoring of it so
choosing is choosing to distract
yourself for example so actively
actively making a choice that will
result in certain actions they're not
necessarily lustful or hateful but are
based upon you know wanting to be self
aware for example so entertainment or
this distraction in general or I'm bored
by myself because I'm aware of
everything it's very unpleasant so I'm
just gonna check some people randomly
not for sensual reasons or because I
hate them just because I want something
to do so often needing things to do is
rooted in delusion
as in in distraction as an indolent on
the level of like you can be very
diligent externally he's doing all this
work but the reasons for you doing their
work are rooted in you wanting to turn a
blind eye in regard to yourself you
don't want to be self-aware basically
you don't see the truth of your mind
well yeah because that will result in
the unpleasant truths of your mind
or simply unpleasant states of boredom
and so on so I better find something to
do I better find an external purpose
doing it will occupy my mind so my mind
won't be aware of itself because being
aware of itself is too unpleasant is too
threatening yeah it's a way of keep
covering up the truth exactly it's it's
the way of maintaining yourself in a
state of cover up keep moving exactly
otherwise if it settles you get to see
what's there and it's unpleasant last
thing yourself is a self aware mmm
sounds like a good thing but yeah it's
like the most painful thing it is yeah
that's where solitude is it is very
unpleasant to begin with that's why the
Buddha himself said many times he
practices so you develop the pleasure of
solitude you won't get it right away if
done rightly it's unpleasant because
you're going against against the grain
of all the distraction you got used to
it and that your existence depends upon
but that's it like when you get into it
when you stop maintaining all these
attitudes of they were based upon
obscuring the self-awareness so when you
stop feeding those attitudes the
self-awareness increases but it feels
like you know the boredom starts giving
rise to dread and anxiety feels like you
yourself are drowning it's crushing you
but what is actually crushing is your
assumed level of your own being the one
that you've been proliferating it's not
actually crushing it like being alone in
your room not seeing you're talkin
anyone cannot do anything to you but yeah your
cannot do anything to you but yeah your
mind can contort of drown in it because
the mind became dependent upon a certain
degree of engagement with the world that
is its threshold but that's not a static
thing that threshold which means the
more you engage the more dependent upon
engage when you become the less engage
well initially he might hurt the lesser
engagement because you used to engage
more but then you get used to that and
then it will not be unpleasant in the
same sense like you have a very hectic
person who's been sort of doing a lot
engaging a lot working a lot for
whatever reasons and then if he was made
to sit down and stop engage into that
level the discrepancy would be just too
much to handle but if he gradually
starts doing that and then start ceasing
his engagement he get used to that new
level of of lacking the engagement that
he used to have which means you're
responsible for the threshold of where
your being is that's what women said his
consciousness gets established upon that
look that becomes the norm that becomes
what you used to it which means anything
less than that it's gonna fill you with
anxiety and dread but it's important to
recognize that it's not a static thing
so through through using engagement with
the world actions meaningless work
whatever else or not not even mean
finding meaning for your work whatever
practically you're engaging with the
world for the means of escaping
self-awareness so you will become
dependent on the lab on that level of
engagement anything less than that
engagement will bring you back to
yourself awareness so that means then
you have to keep maintaining the level
of your engagement and once you get used
to it you have to keep increasing it if
you try to use it to avoid
self-awareness and most people to degree
using it that's what most people are
afraid to be alone not afraid from like
some you know monsters and stuff but
afraid just in broad daylight being left
alone in their room for a whole day
without doing anything without taking my
mind away from myself that's what most
people would be afraid to be left alone
with resulting experiencing anxiety and
existential dread because the human life
on average is about avoiding that
self-awareness which ties in with
avoiding responsibility and feeds one
another and so on but self-awareness is
the thing that's going to make things
right exactly that's what people are
because of their own actions they're
liable to suffering because of that not
because of some someone else's photo or
some design it's because you act in a
manner that keeps making you liable to
suffer keep keeps you exposed so you
could then if you take responsibility
for it that's what what I'm saying might
become apparent that the level of
engagement the level of distraction the
level of turning a blind eye it's not a
static thing which means you can the way
you've been kind of proliferating it you
can then also undo it if you stop
engaging with it or you can certainly
put the brakes on its its growth that's
with abhava in the suitors being again
it's not a metaphysical thing it's it's
the level of your dependence on the
senses which is central being the level
of dependence on the sense of of of the
world the Duty the perception thing you
perceive around the level you depend on
it but then you can start depending less
that's why other hand has cessation of
his being he doesn't depend on anything
but he's still there it's not that the
being means destruction no being means
assumption assumption of engagement
assumption of avoiding responsibility
assumption of censure
and that's what the illusion is ignoring
turning a blind eye distracting yourself
not being able to live with yourself and
again you can ask back onto the
practical level that we always do why is
it that I don't want to be self-aware
why is it that I need to distract myself
from myself cuz it's unpleasant so why
am I then maintaining this whole level
of being for which I'm responsible level
of how much I depend on engagement with
things oh it's because I don't want to
suffer of you suffering exactly yeah so
why do I suffer them oh it's because I
keep running away from suffering that's
why I suffer see if I stop running away
from suffering I at least have a chance
to not suffer it was an example I heard
that people in prison in prison
punishment is solitary confinement and a
lot of people would rather spend their
time with other criminals yeah well it's
not accidental that yeah that was always
the worst punishment solitary
confinement for prolonged periods of
time for an untrained mind of course
you'd rather do things at all bad for
you you would rather expose yourself to
the genuine existential risks then be
alone with yourself I'll jump out of a
plane they take a parachute parachuting
I'll put my life on the line reading all
these extreme sports maybe yeah just to
avoid yeah yeah that's me it's not a
station to think which means avoiding
border needs to be maintained because
you like boredom sets in when you get
used to the threshold then you need to
do more
same with sensuality if people use
sensuality as means of escape if people
get angry as means of escape that's why
I keep getting angrier and angrier as
the life goes by he keep getting used to
it and is he ceases to work your means
of escape cease to work so then you need
to keep running harder the truth is
always there's always pushing so the
fagner the frame that you give into the
attitude of ignoring the truth that's
always there means you're just running
around in a circle you don't really ever
run away
and everybody knows that like if you ask
any random person even not familiar with
Buddhism but can you satisfy your
sensual desires most people who like
already know you can't really you can't
satisfy them you can only run around it
say with anger is the satisfaction of
revenge or inflicting pain back onto
somebody is there really preventing you
from experiencing in the first place no
you know that you just can't help it and
you can't help it because you keep
ignoring the truth you keep ignoring the
nature of what's right in front of you
and Signori will automatically
inevitably result in lust and diversion
in greed and anger and so on but that
doesn't mean that you know if you lock
yourself in the room
and stop engaging with the world that
you will automatically arrive at the
right understanding either because it's
a sad thing that's where the Buddhist
instruction was necessary or the
instruction of somebody externally who
is dunny themselves right away
so the two outcomes for somebody who
hasn't who doesn't have that external
instruction the two outcomes with the
yeah the only two outcomes basically
would be possible if they were to say
lock themselves in either madness as in
the mind would implode because you
wouldn't know the way out of itself oh
you would develop a degree of that self
transparency and undo a great level of
your being which means become more
transparent less subject to suffering
but you have to give in to something you
wouldn't be able to like remain maintain
the transparency all the way to the core
of your being whereby you've undone
every single slightest or existential
discrepancies or slightest of the
conceits as the way they call them and
become another end because if you do
that you would be like self enlightened
so theoretically it's possible but
practically it's highly unlikely but
that doesn't mean that you shouldn't
even try like even even a person who is
not necessarily interested in becoming
fully enlightened and following the
Buddha's instruction to the end it would
do them good
if they start withdrawing the level or
keeping in check the level of their
engagement and dependence on the world
and the senses why because the life will
end in you losing their dependence
sickness aging and death losing your
senses losing the perception the world
losing the things upon which your
existence depends or rather things you
used to maintain the level of being that
sort of helped you to ignore yourself to
that extent to be to be not aware of
yourself and responsibility that's
inherent in that awareness if your life
were truly to last forever and you will
always stay in the control of your
senses yeah that's fun no problem you can do it
yeah that's fun no problem you can do it
but it isn't and you know that everybody
knows that yet you act like you will
live forever and the more you're
dependent on the senses they will
disappear and break apart
the more you'll be affected when that
happens the less you dependent the less
you'll be affected means less you'll
suffer it's like the similar Buddha gave
climbing the tree to eat the mangoes and
eventually somebody's bound to come down
come up and cut that tree because they
can't climb the tree you need the
members or even in the dawn the mangoes
will age and break down and the tree
will fall the higher you were climbed on
their tree the harder you will crash the
more suffering you will experience but
if you kept yourself in check and stay
maybe with lower branches if you
couldn't help yourself back on the tree
in the first place then at least kept
yourself in check use your recent
self-reflection to not proliferate too
far out in practical terms you kept
yourself in check how much in you depend
on distraction how much you depend on
other people other people's company how
much you depend on gratuitous health
senses ability to access the world and
so on and distract yourself with it if
you reflected on it you will keep
yourself in check and then don't go to
one go too far in it so then when you do
get sick when your senses do start to
fail when people leave you or diet or
don't do what you want to do you won't
be as affected because you haven't made
yourself as dependent
but if you are you know you have
concealed so much well oh my
if you concealed so much your whole life
it's never too late to start undoing
their concealment so that's really the
problem there if you never start undoing
your own concealing basically yourself
from yourself
concealing the nature of yourself from
yourself you've never actually faced on
this pleasure yeah never admitted it
where it is
where the problem it is that's what
people are responsible for being bound
to samsara so samsara did binds you you
bind yourself to it and the Buddha says
something's the same effect when he said
it's because people take what's not
theirs what shouldn't be theirs but
cannot be this as if it's theirs and
they act out of it that's why the Mara
does with them what he wants controls
their subjects it all these things what
are the things that cannot be yours and
shouldn't be yours and you keep taking
is yours
and that actually belong to Mara don't
belong to you it's your eyes in your
sights your nose and your smells so
you're very senses the nature of them
shows you that it's not yours you ignore
it you automatically take it as yours
that's we're just turning a blind eye is
enough in itself to result in the whole
mass of suffering it's not like I turn a
blind eye then I do it second step of
taking it is mind then I do this they
know turning a blind eye to the nature
of your senses for example your eyes
your nose your body your life means
automatically implies taking in as mind
because if I ignore that it's not mine
I'm automatically implied that it's mine
that is for me that is in my control and
then you keep acting as if it is your
control and that's how you perpetuate
turning of the blind eye you keep acting
out of it just to stop acting out of it
and then stop doing it internally stop
turning their blind eye start admitting
it go against the grain so that's why
everybody can benefit from solitude to
the extent that they are able to
practice it
but if you don't practice it to fullest
and well you have to take responsibility
for that as well so you might find
yourself out it in too far in life
whereby you can't like just we draw from
everything because there will be
consequences but that's no one else's
responsibility you're responsible for
finding yourself in such situation but
now people realize that that situation
they can't we draw the self from it so
then they feel justified in avoiding
responsibility for it and that's
completely extra yeah you might not be
able you have you have infants in
whatever other family members depending
on you so you can't just leave because
they'll die but that doesn't mean you're
justified now in ignoring responsibility
for that situation that you yourself
built up so yeah you can't ignore the
fact that your choices broaching the
circumstances that now other lives
depend upon you but that doesn't mean
you should take responsibility for it no
matter how late that responsibility
comes the recognition that
responsibility comes it's still better
to take it then to then ignore it
further because who knows to taking
responsibility some new ways and options
might present themselves that you won't
see for as long as you're avoiding
responsibility for it people don't take
responsibility because it's too
unpleasant
they take things become very clear
options become more but because you're
too concerned about not experiencing
discomfort you basically limbs cure and
limit all these options that you could
have otherwise the missile became aware
of yeah
let's we actually get more resilience
less subjected to suffering through
recognize to admit into taking
responsibility it's initially it's more
unpleasant but in a long run it's
actually far more pleasant far less than
Pleasant let's put it like that because
if you think irresponsibility you see
where the problem is and the problem is
in avoiding responsibility that's where
you suffer so you you suffer not because
disagreeable feeling touches you you
suffer because you avoid responsibility
for the suffering in regards
disagreeable feeling you start taking
responsibility for that suffering in
regard to disagreeable feeling you stop
blaming disagreeable feeling for that
suffering which means you stop resisting
it
which means you stop suffering that's it
you stop getting into the domain that
doesn't belong to you
they belongs to mothers you stop taking
it as yours that's it you cannot be
affected by anything it no matter how
disagreeable